[Music]
a
hello everybody and welcome to the 200th
episode of the ask budget show thank you
so much for being here we have crossed
the double century we have touched the
double century mark and it is all thanks
to you that I have been able to reach
here it is all of us together so I would
like to express my gratitude to all of
you all everybody who has been watching
uh this uh show from the first episode
onwards so many people have been part of
the journey and it's a journey that's
continuing we are at a certain stage and
I just want to thank everybody because
this is all because of you if nobody had
been watching if there was no interest
there was no support
then I obviously would not have gone on
to cross 100 and now reach 200 so thank
you to all of you I would like to thank
some people especially first of all I
would like to thank ramal lakmi who
always does the uh time stamps puts up
the time stamps which helps not just me
it helps everybody who watches this
because those of you who want to watch
this later you will get the time stamps
so thank you so much ramama lakmi I
really appreciate that I've never met
you I but you do this selflessly it's so
kind of you I really appreciate that and
the people in the past who have done
that like harid 2.0 Akash Buller and I
would like to thank other people also
who I may not remember right now those
of you who ask questions those of you
who participate thank you so much to all
of you I really appreciate that I am I'm
really grateful to all of you for uh
bringing uh this show to where it is
today okay so uh let me see uh let me
greet a few of you on the live chat who
all is there today
I can see B aush Verma spy threeways
threeways S2 pranu Asura AR arapan goal
pritam Roy American breathing Biden
Biden blast ninja feminist
tuberculosis Karan
nadalini Thank You endan by photo here
one Patel bav aush warma byebye haray
pritam Roy mcloven geopolitical dub
thank you duu goyel netizen Rahul dun
dongar Singh Chan Hello nice to see you
again dongar Singh Chan has been part of
the journey for a very very long time so
appreciate that nitin Kumar VM P tube
Miguel Diaz Cosmic gaming
7781 Tushar kalburgi anjeli pramode pram
Gupta goami Karan nalat hello uh uh so
many of the people AK an prakash Raa
ainash priyan sud who's been here for a
long time thank you so much T Pand uh
prai Paul so many so many of you are on
this live stream warik
zali anurag red ZX
zxx ritwik
acharia and I saw some comments earlier
Telugu man
Artimus um Batman
beats uh
who else spy who is following since
episode 9 thank you so much really
appreciate that uh
swastic sakshi The Observer KL and
everybody else so yeah I'll I'll stop
greeting you all there uh sorry to those
of you who I did not greet in greet
individually but uh greetings to all of
you so I'm going to take some questions
that you have asked in the comments
maybe 15 of those and then I will take
questions from the live chat and maybe I
will do some video chat if I feel like
if if if there is time for that in case
some of you want to ask questions on the
on screen but uh let's take let's go
first with the uh with the questions
that you have asked in the comments
so okay a couple of questions by ad Guru
Prasad views on UK's new prime minister
Kier starmer his party has come to power
after a very long time does the change
in the government in the UK make any
difference will it make any difference
in terms of trade diplomatic ties or
working on anything else together okay
so what are my views on Kier St first of
all the labor party is back in power
after a gap of 14 roughly 14 or so years
um it went out of power it lost the last
elections the last time it was in power
was it 2010 and ever since then it's
been the the conservatives who have in
power mostly if I recall correctly and
Rish sunak has lost the election and
Kier starmer has won in a landslide
victory so yeah it's it's a big change
apparently for the UK but does it really
make any big big difference with the
rest of the world that's what the
question is right so first of all what
are what are My Views about K starmer I
don't know this guy really well he's in
his early 60s or something he doesn't
have a very well defined political
position in the past he has been he has
been uh regarded as soft left uh he
doesn't have any hard stance on on
international relations uh he is all
about uh the development of the
UK and the economic development and
equal opportunity and climate change and
stuff like that which is all
well it's neither here nor there what's
your stance on immigration what's your
stance on the Ukraine war of course he's
going to support the US on that and so
on but no clearly defined stand on any
major issues a very anod kind of person
a guy who who is who no one hates and no
one likes that's that sort of guy but
somehow he has positioned himself in a
place where he now is the new prime
minister so the UK has become kind of a
revolving door Prime ministership people
come and go people come and go that lady
Liz Russ was was prime minister for 50
days Rishi sunak was probably one of the
shortest serving Prime Ministers of the
UK in the 20 in the 20 20 since the 20th
century uh one year in what 200
something days 300 I don't know 200
something days maybe uh one of the short
one of the shorter serving Prime
Ministers of the UK and now we have this
guy so I don't really know what to make
of this guy there he doesn't have any
clearly defined stand on anything he
doesn't really represent anything big or
anything anything powerful he he's just
a guy I guess and that's the kind of guy
if you are a a superpow that's the kind
of guy you want to have in power in one
of your you know one of your wasal
States and obviously the UK is a wasal
of the US so so the revolving door Prime
ministership that the UK has it's it
kind of is reminiscent of what you have
the situation you have in
Japan in Japan also apart from one man
Shinzo AB the others have just come and
gone come and gone come and gone it
doesn't really matter who's the Prime
Minister of the of Japan because at the
end of the day their policies never
change their policy are always what
whatever the US says and the same goes
for the UK so I don't know if he'll make
any significant impact on his on the
fortunes of his Nation uh certainly not
on the global stage International stage
geopolitical stage the UK is not a major
geopolitical Power by any means it is an
instrument that the US uses for various
uh purposes and that's the only utility
the UK has the UK is a reasonably poor
Nation attached to London that's what it
is and it is the you could say the V
victim of of rampant large scale
immigration that no one is doing
anything about and the UK is changing
significantly and it is headed in a
certain direction well I would say all
the best to them that's your it's your
business none of mine uh go with it go
do whatever you want to your country
that's all right with me so I so that's
how I see this guy k starma no real
stand on anything he doesn't have any
flag to PL somewh that this is what I
stand for and this is what I'll do nope
nothing like that is okay uh does this
change in government in the UK make any
difference in terms of trade diplomatic
ET no nothing really will change some
policies internally they will change I
will whatever the the conservatives were
doing labor will try to kind of undo
that and go backwards so five years 10
years the conservatives are on power
they'll they'll Implement certain
policies that have some impact
domestically and then the others the the
labor party comes to power they'll spend
the next five years going backwards been
going in the other direction and then
these guys come back and they go so it's
it's a seesaw kind of thing there's no
real progress in the UK uh so the UK is
kind of a moribund Nation uh I don't
know what sort of future it has
longterm um so yeah that's that's kind
of how I see the UK I don't see any big
change happening in the UK with this guy
and their party and his party coming to
power if if you look at the UK's
international relations it won't change
much it is still very much an extension
of the US uh the UK will continue to
serve whatever purpose the U us has for
it and that's how it's going to be when
it comes to India UK ties I don't see
any significant difference um the UK
will continue to shelter anti-india act
activists and uh separatists and
khalistani activists and all that
they'll continue to do to do that no big
change on the other hand they'll
continue to uh you know pay lip service
to having better ties with India and
they'll certainly want Indian investment
and they'll want to have good economic
ties with India in C directions and all
that so that will continue I don't see
any major change in any of those things
whether it is the the UK's relationship
with the US with India with the EU with
Russia with China or whatever else this
guy is going to make no difference
whatsoever I'm telling you this I think
he's one day into the prime ministership
let me say this right now I usually
don't make predictions I had once made a
prediction about lesz drust that she
will achieve nothing unfortunately it
came true and I'm saying this again when
it comes to this guy Kier starmer is
going to make no lasting impact
whatsoever he's going to implement no
significant new policies and it's going
to be just continuity he may last longer
than his predecessor Rishi sunak perhaps
but just like Rishi sunak just like Liz
druss or whoever else kir starma is
going to make no significant lasting
impact on his Nation or on the world
that's how I see it time will tell us
whether I have I'm going to be right or
wrong but
that's that's how I see it
okay a the Shri and Anand Pai ask
questions about the SE Summit can you
tell us why our prime minister Mr Modi
skipped the SEO Summit why do you think
PM Modi sent Dr SJ Shanker to the SEO
Summit in Kazakhstan aana instead of
going there himself is India sending a
message to China that we don't not take
CO as seriously as bricks what is going
on
okay so yes the SEO Summit uh happened
in aana Kazakhstan and Mr Modi has made
it a point to attend all the previous SE
Summits whenever they happened in person
uh at least five of those if I recall
correctly he has attended so he usually
makes it a point to attend this Summit
the Shanghai cooperation
organization uh and this year he chose
not to go and he has sent his uh well
his Minister Mr his Minister Dr J
Shankar India's foreign affairs minister
to represent him and to represent India
at the summit and the ostensible
official reason that's been given is
that there is a parliamentary session
underway the first parliamentary session
parliamentary session of this new
Parliament right after the first
parliamentary session after the general
election so it's it's an important
parliamentary session and that's why the
Prime Minister needs to attend that
that's the official reason that's been
given well there's nothing significant
happening in Parliament right now
there's no new there's no big debate or
big fight that's happening nothing of
any significance that would need the
prime minister to be there he he could
very much have you know taken a couple
of days out of his schedule to attend
this very important uh event it's
certainly a very important event and
recently the prime minister went to he
attended the G7 Summit
uh in Italy and he usually attends all
these U important
multilateral uh events but this time
he's not gone there so that's
interesting it is certainly interesting
so what could be the reasons for this
well first of all we have to understand
that U India became a member and Prime
Minister Modi attended the SEO Summits
even when India was not yet a full
member India was just an observer and he
yet and yet he attended those Summits
it's only in 2017 that India
was India became a full member of the
Shanghai cooperation organization and
Pakistan was also made a member that
that same year so what could be the
reason for why I mean be be beyond the
official reasons what could be the real
reasons is the question for Prime
Minister Modi not choosing to not attend
the summit has it something to do with
Pakistan does it something to do with
with Russia does it have something to do
with China the Central Asian n Nation
Central Asian Nations what's the deal so
one thing you could think of is it's
about Pakistan because we want to not
have any dealings with Pakistan at any
level and Pakistan is a full member of
the SEO and uh the whoever is the prime
minister currently it's one of the
Sharif Brothers I believe who's the
prime minister right now for now he is
there and we don't want to get you know
to run into these
individuals so Mr Modi will not go there
and he will depute he will ask his
minister to attend so that he doesn't
have to run into the Pakistani guy that
could be one way to look at it but I
don't think that's a
case I don't think that's a case even if
you attend the summit you can simply
ignore the Pakistani uh uh person the
the Prime Minister you can just ignore
the person you don't have to have to go
and talk for him uh so that's not quite
the reason I don't think that's the case
the other possibility you could think of
is that you know there's the Ukraine war
going on the west is obviously it wants
to destroy Russia and the West has been
extremely unhappy with India's
continuing good relations with Russia
India purchasing tremendous quantities
of Russian oil and India refusing to
condemn the Russian special military
operation in Ukraine all of that and
maybe now the pressure has become too
much and now India has had to you know
distance itself from Russia that's
another way you could look at it but
well Prime Minister Modi is going to be
in Moscow
tomorrow well what about that yeah
tomorrow or next week I think 7th e8th
9th something like that in the next
couple of days he's going to be in
Moscow well so then that Russia Theory
doesn't work at all because he's
actually going for a bilateral Summit
meeting with Mr Putin which is something
even more high-profile than a
multilateral kind of meeting with with
other other nations so that theory
doesn't work in the India Russia Rel
relationship is very much on track and
India is making it a point to uh
prioritize this relationship and and
India treats this relationship with a
tremendous amount of importance so that
Russia Theory also doesn't work then
then what's the question do we have a
problem with the Central Asian Nations
kazakistan Tajikistan all that
absolutely not we have excellent
relations with them we would like to
have even better relations with these
nations they are critical to our
connectivity with with Eurasia within
Eurasia with Europe Etc why would we
have any problem with those Nations and
they also need us they would like to
have better relations with us so they
could it could kind of offset the other
powerful Nations Russia and China in the
SEO so what's the deal I'll tell you
what the deal is the deal is China the
problem is
China India I okay so here's the deal
first of all India has right now there's
a very tense standoff happening in the
Himalayan region the disputed boundary
between India and Chinese occupied Tibet
if you want I can put the map on the
screen where's the map here's the map
come on map
here's the map so we have this extremely
long lengthy border with Chinese
occupied the Tibet and that's an
undemarcated border uh because the
Chinese have steadfastly refused to
demarcate the border and there have been
clashes in the past 3 four years along
the border multiple clashes including
the galban Clash when the first firing
happened since the 1980s and the first
time soldiers on both sides died and so
on and the entire crisis which is
ongoing is is uh has been created by the
Chinese India is not the aggressor the
Chinese are the aggressors so the
Chinese are trying to push India on the
back foot but it's not working and uh so
we have this extremely tense situation
in the Himalayan Heights the I perally
Frozen
Heights which are the undemarcated
border between India and Tibet so there
is that and uh so relations between
India and China are not good at all it
is entirely China's fault India does not
claim Chinese territory India has not
started any of the aggression the
Chinese are the ones who are the culprit
who are to blame no matter how they spin
the thing no matter what grandio
language and words about five principles
of whatever Universal priest Brotherhood
they blabber about they are the culprits
when it comes to this they are an
aggressive hegemonic Nation they seek to
bully everybody and it's not working
with
India and if our prime minister were to
go and you know uh make a show of good
relations with SH Jinping that would
tell the world that everything is okay
and India has kind of backed down and
and given into Chinese
bullying so that doesn't work for us we
so we actually want to distance
ourselves from China not from
Russia okay and the Chinese also have
don't have have too many friends in the
world the Russians are unwitting friends
so to say right now but that that that's
the thing so we will not do anything
that uh makes China look good and you
know gives the false impression that
everything is fine with China we will
not talk with China our prime minister
has made it a point that he will not
talk with Mr Shi Jinping he will not go
to any event in which Mr shij Jinping is
there he will depute his
minion to do that right and the fact
also is that the SEO is a China
dominated organiz ation it's the three
major see there are two major economic
powers in the SEO one is obviously China
the second largest economy the second is
India the fifth largest economy soon to
be the third largest economy and the
most powerful military in the SEO is
obviously Russia followed by China and
then India so uh but overall the SEO is
a Chinese dominated organization simply
because of China's enormous economy and
we don't want to give China you know
that win that okay we we got India to
come so that is the thing I think that
India is going to uh going forward place
you know give less importance to the SEO
uh the the bricks is a whole different
story bricks is not a China dominated
organization uh even though China would
like to kind of make it happen that way
but it's not working it's not going to
work that way so uh bricks India will
give it due importance but the SEO India
is going to kind of perhaps it looks
like distance itself from the SEO so I
think the reason why Prime Minister Modi
has chosen to skip the SEO Summit is
because of the of China's aggression
against India continuing aggression
against India and we also don't haven't
forgotten that the Chinese CH the
Chinese leader Mr Shin ping chose to not
attend the G20 Summit in New
Delhi when there was no reason for him
not to attend so we kind of giving it
back even though this Summit isn't a but
it's a Chinese dominated organization so
I think that is the reason that's how I
see it do you have any theories well let
me know in the
comments Abhijit Chava light well that's
a new
one okay the question is does Russia
have the capability to fight the West
all
alone right that's a good question
question so we're talking about fighting
here so what does it mean when you say
fight are we talking about a fist fight
we're talking about a military fight
we're talking about an economic fight
are we talking about a
multi-dimensional fight uh are we
talking about lawfare
Warfare cyber warfare whatever Warfare
so let's see let's assume it's
everything put together okay so what are
Russia's capabil is Visa the West first
of all Russia's economy is not even in
the top 10 okay worldwide uh Russia is
an autarchy which means that it it it
won't be affected by sanctions and it
has not been affected by sanctions
Russia's economy has actually grown
stronger over time the past uh two and a
half or so years ever since the February
22 special military operation started so
Russia's economy is overall okay it is
way more immune to external shocks and
sanctions compared to other Nations but
it is a small
economy uh not even in the top 10 in the
world so so economically Russia cannot
really fight the Americans okay when
we're when we're talking about the West
we are talking about the United States
the US dominates the West the US owns
the West the US runs and operates the
West the Russians cannot fight the West
economically they can withstand
sanctions they can fight a good
defensive campaign economic campaign
against the West they can't fight an
offensive economic campaign against the
West they do not have the means to fight
an offensive economic campaign in West
what about cyber warfare I think the
Russians are really good at cyber
warfare uh so when it comes to cyber
warfare I think they are on even terms
even ke even they're in par West the
west and Russia uh when it comes to
other forms of warfare bio Warfare
chemical warfare I'm sure pretty sure
the Russians are really good at that
okay what about Space Warfare the
Russians have interesting satellites
that apparently can maneuver on their
own and do stuff so they're reasonably
good at that but probably the
Western satellites and capabilities uh
out U outmatch those of Russia
especially with the private sector in
the US taking off Space X and all that
so over that the West has an advantage
what about conventional Warfare when it
comes to Conventional military Warfare I
think the Russ Russians have a very
powerful milit
uh but they do not have the power
projection capabilities that the US has
the US has more than 800 extra
territorial military bases worldwide the
Russians don't even have 20 maybe 20 or
so so the Russians are no match when it
comes to power projection okay
conventional military Warfare uh
technologically the Russians are
developing all kinds of you know 21st
Century weapon systems like drones and
loitering Munitions and suicide weapons
and all that suicide robotic uh
loitering drones all those things Uh
Russian the Russians have good tanks and
good soldiers good infantry good
mechanized divisions and all of that but
overall do they have the ability to
strike at the heart of Europe if they
want to um it's kind of doubtful given
the kind of strength NATO has the
Russians have one of the largest air
forces in the world many of those
aircraft could be kind of old aircraft
you know Mig 31s and so 30s and suco 35s
they have the Su suko 57 which is a
fifth generation fighter plane and all
that uh they are in the process of
developing various uh flying wing
aircraft like the otnc Drone and other
things uh they have so all of that is
there they have excellent cruise
missiles the Russians they have the are
probably the only nuclear powered
nuclear fueled cruise missile in the
world which essentially has unlimited
range all of that but overall militarily
Russia is a very powerful defensive
power it does not have the offensive
capabilities that the US and the West
have okay so it's a great defensive
power but it cannot it it the the
American Air
Force definitely outmatches the Russian
Air Force the American power projection
capabilities completely outmatched those
of Russia Russia is essentially
surrounded by the us whether it is in
the East I mean if if you look at the
map you will see that apart from China
Russia I mean see in the East you have
South Korea and Japan and this uh you
know that kind of encircle Russia you
have Taiwan you have the Philippines you
have all these Pro us Nations that kind
of encircle China and Russia in the west
you have Western Europe that kind of you
know is a barrier against Russia and
NATO has been moving creeping eastwards
and Russia has some ability to project
power in Syria Etc but not too much
compared to uh what the US has and and
nothing else apart from that Russia does
have a significant amount of influence
in Central Asia but that's about as far
as it goes so Russia is a powerful
defensive power can Russia defeat the
West all alone it cannot defeat the West
in a conventional War Russia will lose a
conventional War the us simply has too
many assets the US Air Force itself is
enough to you know take out the Russian
Air Force eventually so where does
Russia have the
advantage Russia has the world's world's
largest nuclear weapons
stockpile it can absolutely annihilate
the US and the rest of the world if it
chooses to but that will be a nuclear
Holocaust which will destroy the whole
world so the Russians obviously want
don't want to do that no one wants to do
that because it will mean the
destruction of the entire planet in
including Russia so that is the last
weapon the Russians have they the
Americans know that if they push too far
uh you know if push comes to shove
something really bad could happen so
overall if you look at all of this put
together the Russians are a tremendously
powerful defensive power but they don't
have the ability to project power and
defeat the West on let's say Western
soil but they have the ability to
destroy the West if they choose to which
will end up destroying the whole world
so that that's where Russia is it cannot
be defeated but it can't
win okay same person abijit
CH asks is Russ is the Russia China Iran
Alliance is it more powerful than the
AIS powers in the second world war does
this Alliance have the potential to beat
the West if World War II happens the
World War II is over I'm I'm guessing
you are asking about the next World War
which we hope never happens World War I
okay so what was the axis Alliance in
the second world war it was Germany
Italy and Japan
essentially essentially these three
powers and some Powers here and there
were had gone along with them so when it
comes to the second world war Italy was
not that much of a big Power the real
big powers in the axis were
Germany and Japan Germany was a
technological superpower at the time
they had the best aircraft they had
pioneered rocketry they had pioneered
cruise missiles and all that but they
were kind of they were a landlocked
nation and eventually they got encircled
and squeezed and smashed by the Soviets
eventually uh Japan a tiny Nation but
tremendous technological abilities and
they had the ambition to be a western
Nation so they be like the west and did
things that the Western nations would do
genocide and occupation and colonialism
and all that so Japan was really
powerful Germany was really powerful now
what about Russia China Iran so this is
a very different kind of
Alliance this time we're talking about
Russia see Russia has Germany in the
second world war we did not have nuclear
weapons until the very end when the
first nuclear weapons were developed and
two of them were tested on Japanese
civilians today the third world war
involves nuclear weapons
it involves war war fighting between
nuclear weapons Powers so when it comes
to Japan uh sorry Russia China Iran
Russia and China are both nuclear
weapons Powers uh Russia has the largest
Arsenal China has a decent Arsenal maybe
300 maybe 500 maybe a th nuclear weapons
we don't quite know how many Warheads
they have but they are a decently
mediumsized nuclear weapons power the
Chinese Iran May perhaps be a nuclear
weapons Power by now uh they probably do
have sufficient file material by now for
maybe a handful of nuclear warheads you
know
tactical Kil kiloton sized nuclear
warheads I'm sure they have some file
material enough for a handful maybe five
maybe 10 warheads and then you have
North Korea which also is part of let's
say this Alliance and the North Koreans
may have enough file material for maybe
20 25 30 nuclear warheads maybe 50
nuclear warheads let's if you want to
you know inflate the numbers a little
bit and uh you have that China is the
world's second largest economy so that
is in China's in this alliance's favor
but if you look at the hard power score
of these
nations uh I had at some point in time
calculated that I think the American
Alliance kind of uh outstrips the hard
power of the China Russia Etc Alliance
and um don't have the calculations right
now on demand
but when it comes to the Pacific Theater
I think the China Russia Etc Alliance
has a significant advantage over the
over the Americans but if you look at
the global theater including the Indian
Ocean the the the Pacific the Atlantic
everything put together I think the
Americans and the West still are more
powerful if you add up the hard power
scores of the coalitions and make them
stand off against each other overall the
Americans still have the advant
AG um so I'm not sure if it's right to
compare the current situation with that
of the second world war there are
significant interesting Parallels for
sure the way the multipolarity is
emerging the way there's a you know slow
bifurcation ongoing bifurcation of the
world order all of that it kind of
parallels what we have seen in the past
during the World War I to Ira the
European Tribal Wars the Western Tribal
wars uh does this Alliance have the
potential to be the West if World War I
happens well if World War II happens
you're going to have fighting we going
to have military action between nuclear
Powers which is extremely dangerous and
if World War II happens and if there's a
single nuke that's used it's going to
end the world so no one's going to win
we all
lose so but if let's assume that nuclear
weapons are not used in that case I
think it's going to cause significant
Devastation uh to
to Russia to China to the us as well
because uh the Chinese will seek to take
out the
American um aircraft carriers and they
have the capability of to do that they
can use swarms of drones maybe 2,000
3,000 drones descending on an aircraft
carrier strike group how many can you
take out and then you can use a
ballistic missile the dong Fang whatever
they have so they can take out American
uh aircraft carrier stri groups then
what do the Americans do they can the
Chinese can take out Guam if they want
they can take out various Japanese
assets the Japanese also will respond
Taiwanese will respond so it's going to
cause a lot of Devastation on both sides
and then if nukes are used we we're done
we fried so we don't want World War I
but overall I think the Americans have
the advantage
overall uh the American lead Alliance
which is the Western Alliance against
the um putative China Russia Etc Iran
North Korea
Alliance okay next question is by Prine
garti Pakistan has started the ASB is is
something foreign language I don't know
something operation on the T Taliban
pashun Pakistan okay P yeah will this
conflict turn into a war between
Afghanistan and Pakistan and will bhat
experience any Spiller of this the
pakistanis in the have done all these
so-called alleged
uh operations against homegrown Etc
terrorists multiple times in the
past I remember there was some operation
Zar
something and all weird names they give
to these operations but they've done a
multitude of such operations and the
objective of these operations is always
to kind of give send a message to the
world that you know we we are an
anti-terrorist nation and we take action
against terrorists and all that uh
especially when they are in trouble and
they need loans from other countries and
these countries are kind of hesitant
because Pakistan is the global epicenter
of Terror so they do these operations
periodically to do to do lip service to
their claim that they are against
terrorism uh and uh they claim that this
uh organization the T Taliban Pakistan
is supported by the Afghan
Taliban and it is given shelter and
support and U material material Aid and
whatever whatever else from Kabul from
Afghanistan obviously the the Taliban
Administration denies this um but in the
past the pakistanis have done
crossborder shelling and operations and
all that uh even air strikes in the past
and now they seem to have started this
new ASB something operation which seems
to be aimed at the Taliban Pakistan so
what is the objective of this operation
is to is to claim to sell this idea to
the world that Pakistan is is see yes in
in its anti-terror stand which is really
funny but okay but what's really
happened I think is the Chinese have
pressurized the pakistanis into
launching this operation because there's
been a lot of uh anti-china sentiment
especially in Western Pakistan in in
Pakistan occupied bistan Etc Chinese
assets Chinese Chinese Engineers Chinese
citizens have been Target tared a few
Chinese individuals have lost their
lives in these operations and all that
so uh and baluchistan if in case you
don't know it it
neighbors uh Afghanistan so you go into
Pakistan and uh baluchistan as you see
north of baluchistan you have
Afghanistan and west of bistan you
obviously have
Iran um so the Chinese seem to have
pressurized the pakistanis into taking
into into launching this uh military
operation so supposedly anti-terrorism
operation and uh that's what it is so it
will certainly if if this operation
progresses I think the operation started
a couple of weeks ago or something and
it's going to be something that's going
to be aimed at Afghanistan in some way
or the
other and the Taliban will not take it
sitting down so there could be some
crossborder activity and you could have
you know some kind of fighting between
the Taliban and the Pakistan Army that
could happen and will this conflict turn
into a war between Afghanistan Pakistan
depends on the severity intensity Etc of
this military operation will the
Pakistan Pakistani Soldiers the the
Armed Forces make crossborder foray into
Afghanistan will they will the target
positions within Afghanistan will the
target Afghan military positions will
the target Afghan civilians will they
actually cross the border into
Afghanistan if that happens that's a
serious escalation and if the Pakistan
don't withdraw immediately then there's
going to be significant uh even more
escalation and if this happens multiple
times you could see an upsurge in the
fighting and that could if in that case
it could actually turn into an
Afghanistan Pakistan war will that
happen well in whose interests is this
and in whose interests is is this not so
you may know hopefully that the well it
is alleged that the Americans are paying
a weekly stipend of maybe 50 or maybe 80
million in cash to the Taliban in
Afghanistan which tells you that
Afghanistan that Taliban is essentially
a US proxy okay in Afghanistan and the
pakistanis are also a US proxy okay so
the Americans obviously will not
want a war between their two proxies
their two vels they don't they will not
want that it looks like the Chinese want
to forment war in this manner and the
pakistanis obviously want to have
multiple Masters that they would like to
have the Chinese on their side of so
that they can offset the Americans uh
that sort of thing the Chinese are
trying to play multiple sides and the
Americans I think will not like this and
the American pressure is way crer than
the than the Chinese pressure so I think
overall I think this will be managed I
don't think it will go out of bounds and
even if there is significant hostility
and and and uh if there are significant
hostilities and military action I don't
think it's going to affect India I don't
think it will affect barhat because the
Afghanistan Pakistan border is on the
other side we currently don't have an
actual land border with Afghanistan as
of now it's a temporary matter but
that's where we are as you can see we
have on the map the you know this this
patch of land which is the border
between India and Afghanistan but as of
now it is in Pakistani hands p Pakistan
ubate Kashmir and Gil baltistan so I
don't think it's going to spill over
into Barat and we certainly have the
capability and the wherewith wherewithal
to prevent any such spillover from
happening okay next
question where's the next
question if it ever comes okay this is
by AEL Chan why does Israel support
aeran with arms against Armenia is it
because of Iran's support for Armenia or
is there more to it also why does Iran
support a Christian State Armenia
against the Shia State aeran insert
mindboggling Emoji so the deal is this
uh the Caucasus region is maybe the
second most
complicated region in the world after
the Balkans the Balkans have this
tremendously
complicated uh
situation extremely complicated history
H it's it's such a mess and I think the
Caucasus region kind of comes close to
that so let's go to the map of the
Caucasus region it's the region between
two between the Caspian Sea and the
Black Sea you know this region here
Southern Russia
uh
Chia and uh dagistan and obviously the
nations of Georgia Armenia and aeran now
as you know azerbijan is a Shia a Shia
majority Nation part of the part of the
earth while USSR so and and Armenia was
also part of the earthw USSR and it's a
Christian Nation probably the oldest one
of the oldest Christian nations in the
world and these two Nations Armenia
aeran have been at loger for a very long
time the Turks tried to destroy Armenia
they conducted an genocide of the
Armenians in Anatolia in Turkey there
was a significant an Armenian population
in Turkey which no longer exists and the
Turks and the AER Banis would like to
see Armenia be wiped off the map so that
they can create a panan corridor all the
way to Turkmenistan all the turkic
nations now
tan Iran is a Shia nation and Iran has a
significant well you know Iran is an
ambitious Nation so so is
turkey and these two nations are are
obviously on opposite sides when you
have two reasonably powerful nations
with the border they will never be
friends and they have conflicting uh
Ambitions and so on and so forth so uh
aeran despite being a Shia nation is a
turkic nation okay and it it is very
much an ally of turkey you could say
it's a proxy of turkey Iran has a
significant AER bani aeri population in
this region in the aeran province of
Iran and Iran is worried about the aeran
it's aeran
citizens who may perhaps be inclined to
support turkey and
aeran and uh Israel sees Iran as a
mortal enemy that's why they support
aeran and
Armenia despite being a Christian Nation
because turkey and aeran are against
Armenia and if Armenia disappears then
it will be it's a disaster for Iran
that's why Iran supports
Armenia and Russia is also involved I'm
not going go into that it's a very
complicated matter India and Iran are
essentially supporting Armenia and
Israel is on the other side is
supporting turkey and aeran in this
matter so it this goes beyond religion
okay at the end of the day power is not
about religion it's geopolitics is not
not about religion it's about national
interests and National Ambitions and
when you have Islamic Nations like aeran
and Iran and turkey with conflicting
Ambitions then they will be happy to
support a non-islamic nation
to to advance their objectives and their
Ambitions that's how it goes it's very
complicated matter but I hope I've given
a reasonably uh good overview of what's
Happening next question is by rodit
sarar can you tell something about the
Monroe Doctrine did the US successfully
implement the doctrine does India follow
any such Doctrine okay what was the
Monroe Doctrine uh there was this guy
called James Monroe who was one of the
presidents of the US in the first
quarter of the 19th century and this
Doctrine was put in place in
1823 if I am not mistaken and this
Doctrine
stated that
uh that that European colonization will
no longer be allowed in the Americans in
the Western Hemisphere let's take a look
at a a map of the
Globe okay and what's the Eastern
Hemisphere what's the Western Hemisphere
the Western hemisphere is essentially
everything uh west of uh west of the UK
okay you you draw a
line across the the globe from the North
Pole to the South Pole west of the UK of
the British Islands everything west of
that is the Western Hemisphere and there
are two hemispheres eastern and western
okay so the entire West Western
Hemisphere essentially is the Americas
North America and South America and the
Monro Doctrine was said that European
colonization in the Americas and the
Western Hemisphere would no longer be
tolerated it would be regarded as a
hostile activity hostile action by the
US and the US will not allow this it
also said that whichever European uh
colonies already exist existed in the
Western Hemisphere the Americans would
not uh do anything about that they will
allow them to exist but no new Colonial
activity will be allowed and so on so so
forth um so it was all about uh the US
saying that we now own the Western
Hemisphere um and initially in the
initial years the British supported the
Americans and they enforced the Monro
Doctrine the British at that time the UK
was more powerful than the US okay and
they had a much more powerful navy than
the US and they actually supported the
US in that the UK uh but in the N late
19th century the Americans developed a
powerful navy they became more powerful
than the UK and so on and then
eventually the nro doctrine took the
form took such a form that the Americans
said that they would have the right to
interfere in any nation in South America
if it went against American interests
and they did that they you know they did
much of that they invaded and occupied
various Nations and did regime change
operations and then conducted elections
to make all everything look good and so
on so forth that was the Monro Doctrine
but how did this
happen we have to understand the history
right this guy Monro puts forth the
doctrine in in in in 1823 but what was
the background for this the background
for this Doctrine was the Napoleonic
Wars Napoleon bonapar was the emperor
eventually of France and Italy and
he of the world kind of following the
footsteps of Julius Caesar kind of and
he fought everybody he fought every
single European power and he was very
successful initially but eventually he
was exiled to the island of s St Helena
in
1815 so because of the Napoleonic Wars
various European nations like Spain
Portugal Etc lost contact with their
colonies in South
America and the governors they had
installed in these colonies they became
independent rulers and these nations
gained independence because the European
powers were too busy being embroiled in
the Napoleonic Wars which a period which
lasted what 15 20 years roughly roughly
maybe less look it up so because of
Napoleon's Wars in Europe the various
European colonies in Latin America
became
independent and then the Americans said
okay the time is right for us to now
make our move and in 1823 but they put
forth the the Monro Doctrine so the US
initially needed a British helped to
implement the doctrine but eventually it
became powerful enough to enforce it on
its own in the late 19th century and in
the 20 in the 20th century does India
follow any such Doctrine India is not
powerful enough to follow any such
Doctrine okay if you look at India's
neighborhood India does not follow a mro
Doctrine uh you have Nepal in which
there is clear Chinese interference
which we ourselves have created the
situation that that has you know enabled
this to happen our go governments
in the late 19 in the late 20th century
the 1990s 2000s you know essentially um
um enfor not enforced but but enabled
regime change in Nepal and the
destruction of the last Hindu monarchy
in the world and the Takeover of Nepal
by the Communists maoists and pro-china
elements so we allowed this to happen
our governments allowed that to happen
we don't have a mro doctr we have an
anti-ro Doctrine we we want everybody in
our neighborhood to be Inu by others we
have so we have Chinese interference in
Nepal we have Chinese interference in
Bhutan the Chinese claim Indian
Territory uh Bangladesh is is fine there
is tremendous us interference in in
Myanmar The Americans are are bullying
Bangladesh right now they want to carve
out a Christian Nation out of Burma
Bangladesh and Manipur the Americans
okay um there is Chinese interference
over here the the
burmes they gave a couple of islands to
the Chinese in the Andaman
sea uh when it comes to Sri Lanka there
used to be Norwegian and Western
interference there Pakistan is is a
puppet of the US Afghanistan is is kind
of you could say a soft wasal of the US
so everywhere around India there is
external interference and allegedly
there is even external interference
within India itself so India doesn't
follow a mro Doctrine India should
follow a mro mro Doctrine but that can
that you can only do if you are powerful
enough you need to be a genuinely
powerful
Nation so India may be 20 years away
from that and the powers that we want to
ensure that this never happens so yeah
it's it's a kind of a very important
phase in India's history make or break
kind of phase right now India doesn't
have the ability to follow to enforce an
Indian version of a Monroe
Doctrine next question
Oopsy Daisy okay here we are it's by
goami many times you said leadership is
very important for the development of a
country but say Japan Germany or EU
countries these nations developed very
rapidly after the second world war
despite not having any good leaders and
now they are almost developed countries
well the EU is fully developed Japan was
definitely fully developed Germany as
well so do you agree that leadership
does did not really play much of a role
for the development M of these nations
but their education policies played a
much bigger role during the time of
development what are your thoughts
interesting question and I'm glad that
people try and find loopholes so that
they can
challenge various statements which is
good which is good so what's the deal uh
I have always said and I still say that
leadership is the most crucial thing
that a nation has without great
leadership you will never have a good
future
the quality of leadership is the most
important thing in the long-term
development in the long-term future of a
Nation think about it like this H let's
say you have I have spoken about this
before but let me give you this example
again so that you understand okay let's
say you have a nation whose inhabitants
are sheep you know sheep B sheep so you
have a nation whose inhabitants are
sheep none of these sheeps sheep has any
leadership qualities no good leader
okay but they have the Good Shepherd who
takes care of them and they have
territorial Integrity the the enclosure
of the sheep is taken care of no wolf
can come inside and the sheep have a
great lifestyle they have tremendous
development they have good facilities
for for sleeping for shelter Against the
Wind and the rain and whatnot they have
copious quantities of food and they are
all in great health free health care is
there everything is great okay a fully
developed nation of the sheep but no
leaders but what's really happening
what's really happening every day one or
two sheep disappear right where do they
go they they think they're going
somewhere for a walk and and all and
eventually they realize they've reached
the slaughter house
so when so that's an example for you to
kind
of ponder about okay development isn't
enough do these wonderful sheep who are
enjoying this luxurious lifestyle do
they have the right to
self-determination do they have self
determination do their descendants have
a great long-term future Prosperity
Independence
self-determination do do do they
have self-determination in terms of
their lifestyle and culture no they are
following a lifestyle imposed on on them
by somebody else sheep actually want to
climb Hills and you know be in rugged
places but they are being made to sit in
an large enclosure and just relax it's
an unnatural lifestyle for them so my
point is this Japan is a nation under
foreign occupation us occupation
permanent us occupation so is Germany
the US needed to create an alternative
to the system that the USSR was showing
to the world so they needed Nations to
encircle the USSR they needed the entire
Western World the NATO dominated world
to emerge and they needed needed these
countries to be powerful and prosperous
but but controlled by
them okay and they needed to show the
world that see our system is better the
Nations where you have the American
system the Western Le system these
nations are prosperous they have good
Lifestyles great living standards great
economies but who did these economies
serve they served the us because all of
these nations were well part of the what
do you call it
the the US dollar was was King wasn't it
and when it comes to the bank of Japan
when it comes to every single decision
taken by Japan in terms of foreign
policy Economic Policy military policy
it was all dictated by the US so it
served the US interest the same goes for
Germany yes these nations were
prosperous but these nations can be
destroyed like that what's happening to
Japan now it was the world's second
largest economy in the
80s it was threatening to surpass the us
today Japan is becoming a middle income
Nation it's going backwards backwards
backwards look at Germany it's under
recession how did this happen to Japan
how did this happen to Germany well read
of the plaza Accords the Americans
destroyed the Japanese economy in a very
slow motion decline since the 80s what
happened to to
Germany northstream 2 the Germans needed
any powerful economic machine needs
copious and cheap energy you cut that
off the economy dies it starves that's
what's happening to Germany right now
Germany is in recession the economy the
economic Miracle is over the Americans
can create this they can destroy
this you may have a welldeveloped
country but if the fate of your nation
is not in your hands or in the hands of
leaders who genuinely represent you then
you can be taken out any time and that's
what's happening right now leadership is
crucial it is critical it is
non-negotiable oh yes I have great
living standards tomorrow it will be
taken away then
what your fate your destiny has to be in
your own
hands okay
development without being in control of
your destiny means you are being
developed for somebody else's
benefit the Sheep are being fattened so
that they can be slaughtered when the
time is right that's the deal leadership
is critical it is crucial it is
non-negotiable let's say a very bad
hypothetical example which will never
happen but let's say India becomes a us
vasal or a Chinese vasal okay right now
it's not let's say it happens and they
develop India okay they they impose a
wonderful education system on India and
they give great living standards and all
and they will make sure that you your
culture is wiped out and you become a
market for them to dump their goods in
and you don't produce anything but you
only give
services and then when the time is right
they'll pull the plug and everything
will disappear and you will have nothing
left so you don't want that you need
great leadership great leadership is
non-negotiable it is critical without
that you are nothing you're dead please
understand that please understand
that rajat says when do we send back the
illegal immigrants to the respective
countries and when that happens how will
the Foreign Relations change with those
countries and where is the chavda index
first of all chavda index it's it's done
but I need to make the website
presentable before I release it so could
happen in a couple of weeks yeah it is
done it's it's the index of hard power
Global hard power rankings it'll come
out soon and thank you for the reminder
I appreciate that uh about illegal
immigrants in India so we have an
illegal immigration problem mainly it's
Bangladesh is and various individuals
who are who were once based in Burma
ring and the so-called
cookies so we eventually will need to
send them back to the respective
countries the cookies I don't even know
if they're burmes because they don't
speak the burmes language they don't
respect the burmes culture traditions
and all that they actually maybe from
from yunan or something they don't have
any allegiance to Burma or to India even
though they may claim whatever when it
comes to the ringas again they don't
have any allegiance to Burma they don't
have any allegiance to India but they
want to live in India and and enjoy all
the benefits when it comes to Bangladesh
is
well what can I say why how many do we
have Bangladesh is at least 50 million
if not 100 million in India uh so yeah
there is a big problem and we are doing
thus far nothing about this horrific
problem uh so let's say the government
of India if surprisingly gets its act
together and decides to repatriate these
illegal infil infiltrators back to their
respective countries let's say the
unthinkable happens let's say a miracle
happens and the government wakes up and
does that what's going to happen will it
spoil India's relations with those
Nations well it depends on how we deal
with those
governments of course if we send back 50
million Bangladesh to to Bangladesh it's
going to cause a huge amount of pressure
on the local economy on the Bangladeshi
economy so all their excess Riff Raff
they're sending to India and we are
absorbing that and we are absorbing that
pain so right now our economy has to
support 50 million 100 million extra
individuals who actually give nothing
back to the country so let's say we
identify them all and Deport them to
Bangladesh let's say 50 million people
it's going to cause a tremendous amount
of hardship immediately to Bangladesh
but that's not our problem right these
are not our people so will that cause a
deterioration in the relationship
between India and Bangladesh it could or
maybe not uh if we deal with the
government of Bangladesh properly and we
explain that this needs to be done and
you need to take this and we're going to
maybe help you out in some way maybe it
works fine but the opposition
politicians in Bangladesh will
definitely raise a human cry and they
may use this as the means to defeat the
shik H government or the current
government in future elections so it is
it's one way or the other it will have
some
repercussions but that doesn't mean that
we should keep on saddling ourselves
with this unnecessary unneeded burden of
low quality individuals who are not
Indian citizens but benefiting from the
Indian economy we need to get rid of
them in a in a dignified civilized
manner means rep repatriate them uh dep
them and repatriate them to their
country same goes for the individuals
who have uh you know emerged out of
Burma the the ringas and the the cookis
two very different classes of
individuals but both neither are Indian
citizens so this needs to happen Burma
no longer even has a government it's
kind of a lawless place right now
complete Civil War situation the burmes
government the the
officially the official government is
not in control of the entire nation
maybe half the nation there are all
these rag tag tribal groups running amok
everywhere and behind all of this is a
very well-crafted organized coordinated
campaign by the church and by the United
States who have geopolitical reasons for
doing this uh long long it's it's a
complete mess actually as far as we are
concerned but if India does Deport all
the all these individuals to various to
these countries we will have to deal
with Bangladesh properly if we do this
when when it comes to Burma there's half
the country there's no government you
can just push them back uh yeah but
you've got to put your National interest
first long-term National interest first
you cannot sacrifice your long-term
interests for the sake of short-term
expediency and that is something I hope
the government understands and
realizes okay Imran naimi says why do
Iranians call their language fary I've
have read many books including the
shaame and the works of famous poets but
they call the language Dari rather than
farsy in old books I did not see a
language called fary but darari why is
that are the Iranians concealing the
truth and why are the majority of
mathematician scientist and Poets born
in Afghanistan why are they referred to
as as Iranians Irani in Google is this
not an example of Injustice or
unfairness good good question yeah so uh
the poran language has evolved over at
least 3,000 years okay uh the aid
Dynasty the hakam dynasty the language
spoken at that time was old person which
was kind of like an up Branch daughter
language of Sanskrit read the bhasan
inscription beist inscription it sounds
like a slightly modified version of
Sanskrit with with slightly different
pronunciation but apart from that you
can actually understand what's written I
can understand what's written there
because it sounds so similar to to
Sanskrit uh and so on that was old
person then you had middle person then
you had uh then you had something called
new person okay which was which was
spoken during the sassanian times and
the sasanians were invaded by the Arabs
and that's when the islamization of of
Persia happened and fosi lived roughly a
thousand years ago and fosi wrote The
Shame in the new persan language which
is the person that is kind of still
spoken today okay
now you are right Iman Nami that at that
time about a thousand years ago the
language was called Dari it was the
dialect of persan that was spoken in the
in the court the Royal Court of the
sassanian
uh you know
Kingdom that's the kind of thing it was
for for example the hindustani language
the Udu language is the language that
came out emerged out of the military
camps and courts of the Turks who ruled
India for some time similarly the new
persan language emerged as a dialect
which was spoken in the courts of the
sassanian Kingdom Etc during the Arabic
occupation and all that um and the
language has remained pretty much stable
the past thousand or so years primarily
because of the influence of the shaame
of of fosi but fosi was not the first
writer who wrote in this new Persian
language which was called Dari at the
time I think there was a guy called
rudaki rudaki who was who was born in
presently Tajikistan who was the first
writer in this language let's let's uh
see what Google has to say about rudaki
let's go to
rudaki I'm not sure if I'm pronouncing
it right but let's see r u d a k
i rudaki okay so this guy was a poet
singer musician Etc uh who regarded as
the first major poet to write a new
person that's right and he was born
where
uh he was under the samanids he composed
more than 180,000 verses only a small
portion of his work has survived most
notably a small part of his
versification of the kalila VNA a
collection of Indian fables which was a
panchatantra a Persian uh version of the
panchatantra anyway some of that has
survived he was born in the rudak area
which is in Western Tajikistan all right
so he spoke he he was the first major
person poet to write in new portion
and it was called
Dar it was called Dar but now it is
called fary right it's called farsy now
so what does fary mean first of all it
should be Pary not fary because Persia
is Paras right the the land of the
Parsha people the descendants of the
paraa clan so it should be Pary the
persans who escaped the Arabic invasion
of Persia and came into India they are
still called
Pari so the language should be Pari but
because the Arabs don't know how to say
p they replace that with far and that
Arabic pronunciation tradition has kind
of continued in Persia which is why the
language is called Farsi but the
original term for the language of the
new person language was Dar and today
you today in
Afghanistan the language is still called
Dari and it's essentially the same as
the the P language the farsy language
which is spoken in Persia but maybe some
differences maybe some some minor
differences and there is a Dari that is
spoken in Tajikistan as well I think
it's called tajiki these days so every
nation wants to give its
own uh own name to the language but it
is the same language
essentially uh so yes you are right the
language was originally called Dari not
Farsi and you even the farsy name isn't
right it should be Pary so I'm not sure
if the Iranians are concealing the truth
maybe they don't even know the truth
maybe it's the truth has gone so far
back that you don't know about it they
don't know about it and lots of
scientists poets Etc Scholars were
certainly born in Afghanistan but
because they wrote in the Persian
language they are incorrectly called
Iranians or whatever on Google I think
it's not the fault of the Iranians of
the people of Iran I think it's the
fault of the western Scholars who write
the history of the world and then we
just follow that blindly the West
oversimplifies everything they don't
understand our people look India
Afghanistan Persia the subcontinent Etc
we are very different from the West we
are a very
complex people we have a very old
ancient history the westerners don't
understand us okay and they try to
oversimplify everything and they
obviously in
their um they have the superiority
complex that they they will decide what
what the world is like and everybody has
to agree agree with that so they will
write our histories and then that
distorted incorrect history version of
History will then be slavishly taught in
our education system I'm sure there is
this significant uh inferiority complex
in Persia as well I mean the Persians
believe in the Arian Invasion myth the
Persians use many French words in their
language the Persians what is Mercy
huh you don't you don't have a word of
your own what's
Mercy why do the persons use the word
mercy I mean I know you don't want to
use shukran or whatever I'm sure you
have a word of your own why do you have
to use foreign words but that's the deal
even the persans try
to do that there is an inferiority
complex there um so it is what it is our
history has been distorted tremendously
we in India know that very well by now
at least some of us are waking up to
that I've been saying that for a very
long time and the subcontinent
Afghanistan Persia the same thing
applies
everywhere so there is a lot of uh stuff
that you know a lot of achievements that
came out of Afghanistan that are
incorrectly ascribed to Iran I mean
zaratustra the the you know the the
founder of the Zoro asan religion he was
born in Afghanistan in gandhar he was
not born in Persia okay so there is that
also and I'm not sure how many people
know that
Z so it is definitely unjust it is
unfair but I'm not sure if if the
Persians are responsible for this
Injustice and unfairness the Persians
are simply following the West the lead
of the West like like most people do in
India as well if an Indian historian
says something Indian scholar says
something nobody believes that but if
the same thing is spoken or written by a
Westerner a wh skinned guy oh my God yes
yes that is the gospel truth that's how
it is so it's not just India it's the
entire region that suffers from The
White Man's
Burden
right okay next
question okay here we
are waiting for it to
appear uh well give me a second
okay this one will appear will this
appear now okay here we are RIT sarar
says did ancient India establish any
InterContinental trade routes like the
Silk Road which land and sea routs did
ancient Indians use to trade with other
countries okay let's go back to the map
where's the map here's the map India
obviously had a tremendous amount of
trade with significant portions of the
world for example there we have
found U sarasvati synu Ira outposts in
present day Oman you know Port region
ports at least one port I know of which
was essentially an Indian Outpost in
Oman from the Saraswati Hindu period the
harapan period of India's history so we
had that okay and during the the Saras
Sindu era the Hara we were trading with
Mesopotamia that is well known and the
Mesopotamians
they called us
Mila uh so we were trading with them
then we know that Indians were trading
with Egypt about 2,000 BC or so
thereabouts We There is evidence of
that
uh we know that the in Indian bull the
the zebu bull the Indus Valley bull
first appears in Egypt around at least
around 2,000 BC or something which is
4,000 years before today so we were
trading with that
so we had this sea route via the
straight of hormos into the Persian Gulf
region and from there we would trade
with Mesopotamia and when it comes to
Egypt we would trade while the Gulf of
Adan and the Red Sea and go all the way
to
Egypt uh then I'm sure we had uh
Overland trade routes uh with Central
Asia
Etc and we after China emerged as a
civilization we were trading with
China Overland which which we now call
the Silk Road but it was going on for a
very long time we were definitely
trading with
suomi the great people of Kalinga were
trading with suomi which is southeast
Asia Thailand Myanmar Etc Cambodia
Vietnam all the way for at least 3,000
years before today and that was trade
done across the sea VI ships so there
was that and we know very well for a
fact that India had a tremendous amount
of trade with the Roman Empire uh we
were exporting uh our Goods to the
Romans finished goods and spices and all
that and in exchange for that the Romans
were sending
India gold gold coins and so
on so there were multiple trade routes
and Indians have been living in Eastern
Africa for for centuries maybe thousands
of years uh and that also was definitely
happening y SE so we had ships and
Indians were s had settled down in this
region Madagascar Bambi Tanzania Kenya
Somalia Etc the entire east coast of
Africa is deeply deeply influenced by
India so we had India has always been a
maritime civilization a ship building
civilization from the days of the Riga
so we leveraged that those technological
abilities to trade with so many parts of
the world so that was the deal and I can
give you examples you know hard evidence
of Indians uh of Indian Merchants let's
say Indian Traders uh having a presence
in the Roman Empire let let's go to our
friend Google and let me show you
something
interesting so Indian Indian
statue in what was it
pompe so they disco archaeologists have
discovered an Indian statue with a style
that's similar to chra Chandra kugar or
gandhar in Rome in in one of the Villas
in this
region and uh this clearly was the home
of an Indian Merchant who was living in
Pompeii maybe maybe it's goddess lakmi
maybe it is a yakshi or something we
don't know quite who this lady was but
it is clearly an Indian statue that is
100% sure and it was discovered in
Pompei so an Indian Merchant was living
in a villa in Pompei and Pompei as you
may know was uh destroyed in a
catastrophic volcanic eruption Mount
vvus destroyed the cities of Pompei and
herculanum around 180 roughly 8080 180
look it up if you're interested so
that's evidence of trade and we have
tremendous amounts of gold coins vases
amoras Etc on India's East Coast on
India's West Coast found all over the
place which all originates in Rome so
that tells you there was a tremendous
amount of trade so there's ample
evidence of India trading with with
Mesopotamia India trading with uh India
having outposts in u the Arabian
Peninsula 4 5,000 years before today
India trading with Egypt 4,000 years
before today and India trading with Rome
2,000 years before today and India
trading with southeast Asia at least
3,000 years before today tremendous
trade and China came later China emerged
around 3,000 years before today and we
started trading with them
about I think during the mo in IRA and
afterwards when the Chinese became an
actual
civilization so we've been trading with
everybody we've always had this uh
policy we that we want to be friends
with everyone we'll trade with everyone
we'll have relations with everybody good
relations we've always been that sort of
culture and
civilization RIT sarar again says in
ancient times did people from other
dharmic countries come on pilgrimage to
the holy sites of Hindus and Buddhists
in Barat in India yes of we clearly know
about the
people from Eastern Asia who came to
India for a variety of reasons uh many
of them came for Education many of them
came in search of knowledge and wisdom
and sacred Indian texts philosophical
texts religious texts whether it is
dharmic texts Hindu text Buddhist text
whatever we know of swanang who came
from during the Tang Dynasty who came on
an arduous long long journey to India
the moment he reaches gandhar the the
the uh bamya Valley he says thank God
I'm finally in India and then he comes
further down south and all that so we
know of him we know of many pilgrims
from many other Chinese and Korean
pilgrims who studied in Nanda they would
actually spend a year or two in
Indonesia to study Sanskrit and prepare
themselves for the entrance exam in
Nanda but that that is obviously about
studies but uh you had pilgrims coming
in from various parts of the world for
religious reasons as well and let's me
let me show you an interesting
interesting piece of information now you
may have heard about the Shri pad banava
Swami Temple right Shri padas Swami
temple in Kerala now let's take a look
at what Wikipedia has to say about this
a statutory warning Wikipedia is not
always a reliable source of information
but let's see what Wikipedia has to say
about this Temple and why am i showing
you this right now so uh we know the we
know know right it's got a tremendous
amount of wealth this Temple so uh it's
got a
treasure
um and uh what do we know okay there's a
tremendous treasure that has been
recovered I mean it's not been recovered
it is it is known to exist there and it
has somehow escaped the greedy grasping
claws of the British and other Invaders
of India occupiers of India the treasure
found so far is considered to be by far
the largest collection of items of gold
and fully precious stones in the r
recorded history of the world just one
Temple okay and we had hundreds of such
temples in India so tremendous amount of
wealth now where did this wealth come
from right that's the
question so these valuables are believed
to have been accumulated in the temple
over several thousand years so this
Temple is mentioned in Tam Tamil in
sanum literature it's thousands of years
old okay by this way by the way it's a
golden temple it is the original Golden
Temple the true Golden Temple of India
so the valuables are to have been
accummulated in the in the temple over
several thousands Thousand Years having
been donated to the DT and subsequently
stored there by various dynasties our
dynasties like the cheras pandas tranor
royal family The KES the palavas Chulas
and many other kings in the recorded
history of both South India and Beyond
and from the rulers and Traders of
Mesopotamia Jerusalem Greece Rome and
various Colonial powers from Europe and
other countries as well you understand
that okay
uh what evidence do we have of that I'll
tell you what evidence we have of that
let me look up and down somewhere we're
going to find something over
here what did they find in this place
let me look for a specific
keyword
okay uh the objects include lacks of
golden coins of the Roman
Empire lacks hundreds of thousands of
golden coins
from the Roman Empire and much more
stuff okay so this is just one example
that tells you that there were Kings
from Mesopotamia from Jerusalem from
from Rome and and various other parts of
the world who are donating tremendous
amounts of treasure to this
Temple there were Merchants there were
Kings there were rulers and travelers
and visitors and whatnot who were
donating uh tremendous amounts of wealth
to this Temple let me show you another
thing okay show you another example once
again let's go to our friend
Google okay have you heard of the rupon
lake rup kund lake so very uh in you
know
intriguing Lake and something very
strange happened there ancient DNA of
skeletons so it's a lake in utarak in
Northern India it's it's half half the
time it's frozen and this lake is KN is
known for a tremendous number of
skeletons that are found there okay
skeletons that are lying
there and recently these skeletons have
been DN tested so this is what the lake
looks like it's a reasonably small Lake
and it has a tremendous number of
skeletons there human skeletons and the
Mystery is what who are these people who
are the people who died there why did
they die what did they die of so what
does the journal Nature have to say
about
this let me okay let me accept
unfortunately the cookies you see Dr NJ
R who has been on the podcast he is part
of this study so it and and these people
this is a pilgrimage region okay it's a
place of pilgrimage the utarak region so
several hundred individuals of Unknown
Origin scattered skeletal rins so they
did a DNA genomewide DNA thing of etc
etc they cluster into three distinct
groups a group of 23 individuals of
ancestry that falls within the variation
range of variation of present day
subcontinental people further 14 have
ancestry typical of the Eastern medit
Anan and we also identify one individual
with Southeast Asian related ancestry
these remains were not deposited
simultaneously uh the Indian origin
people they died around 800 CE but
evidence of being deposited in more than
one event all the other individuals the
Eastern Mediterranean Etc died died
around 1800
CE okay and these were most likely
pilgrims who had come on a pilgrimage to
the sacred land of
utarak people from the Eastern
Mediterranean region what is the Eastern
Mediterranean you ask well let's go to
Google maps in case you are wondering
what the Eastern Mediterranean is the
Eastern Mediterranean region is Lebanon
Israel Cyprus
Syria Egypt turkey Etc so individuals
from there had come to the rkun
lake for pilgrimage purpose there's no
reason no other reason for them to be
there so you had this going on in India
India is a very strange
intriguing weird place where people come
from all over the world for pilgrimages
Steve Jobs came to India in search of
religion Steve Jobs he became a disciple
of nim karoli Baba and he died with with
what autobiography of a yogi in his hand
and he had that book distributed on in
in his funeral so India is that sort of
land
okay okay next
question as always it won't come up
okay okay the questions are not popping
up today for some reason okay it came
and disappear okay here we are this is
by uh arapan
goal can we say that India was really an
independent nation before 1764 when the
British won the Battle of buxer as our
textbooks say the Delhi sulate and the
muls had ruled India for for much more
time than the British so shouldn't we
consider them them to be occupiers who
destroyed India much before the British
or the other Europeans okay so what's
the deal let's go to our friend Google
once more and let us discover what was
the deal before before that date that
you mentioned
1764 okay marata Empire
1759 let's say
okay let's go to Google imagis and see
what this has to say this was the marata
empire in
1758 okay and if you look properly it is
essentially the entirety of India so
before 1764 when the British won the
Battle of
buxer India bhat was essentially the
marata Empire we were not an independent
nation we were an independent Empire we
were an independent civilization the
maratas had liberated India from the
Turks from the foreigners and
essentially established they called
hindavi
swaja and the British destroyed that
okay the British did not defeat the
Turks the so-called mugal the British
defeated the Hindu marata Empire that's
what the British did to India so your
favorite historians many of them will
claim that the British saved India from
the Turks the mugal I'm sure many of
your teachers will will claim that those
individuals are
ignorant this is another representation
of the marata Empire 1759 and the
capital of of the empire was Pune at the
time so there you have it okay uh and of
course you are right the the Turks they
ruled various parts of India not the
whole of India but they ruled various
parts of India for for
several centuries not the entirety of
India here there the Delhi Sate and
various other patches of India and all
there were the whole of India but they
did do that and they caused a tremendous
amount of harm to
India so yes the Delhi suanet the Turco
muls Etc they are indeed occupiers of
India foreign Invaders and occupiers of
India who destroyed India destroyed did
a tremendous amount of damage and harm
and and material and and damage and
genocide in India the worst genocide the
world has ever seen much before the
British and the other Europeans so I
agree with
you now we will go to the next
question if it loads there's a problem
with the questions loading
today
okay let us see if the question
loads okay here we have it uh gami has
two questions mcau Lord babington mcau
right that guy he has always been blamed
in India as much but as much as I have
read and know the game had already been
prepared before M's arrival in India he
just came and played played his Innings
okay I've always read that M's idea was
the downward filtration Theory but it is
mentioned on Wikipedia that Alexander
Duff the Scottish missionary proposed
the theory which he called the downward
filtration Theory
okay so the British East India Company
came to India for the purpose of trade
okay they knew that India was this
tremendously Rich prosperous
subcontinent and they wanted to trade
with India and become rich in the
process so the British e India Company
was created uh sometime around the time
that uh Elizabeth died the daughter of
Henry
thei and it had stake shareholders Etc
in in in in London and they started
trading with India and then eventually
after a few centuries they started
running India ruling India so their
objective was to trade with India and
and the objective the purpose of the
company was entirely commercial
so
um and then what happens is that they
start taking control of various parts of
India and then British missionaries
wanted to come to India and uh try
harvesting Souls soul vultures right
they are so the East India Company
opposed that and the East India Company
the the people who came to India the who
wrote about India were extremely they
wrote very positively about India and
India's culture and that's how the
awareness of India started building up
in the UK and in Europe and then
missionaries wanted to come to India and
then the missionaries they had very
powerful lobbies in Parliament and
eventually they were able to convince
the British Parliament to allow
missionary activity in India so this
begins around the late 18th century
early 19th century somewhere around that
time by this time the East India company
starts gaining a lot of power in India
and the moment the missionaries set foot
in India they start writing atrocity
literature about India all kinds of
horrible uh depictions of India because
if you want to destroy a culture
civilization and introduce Christianity
you have to first convince the natives
that they are barbaric and they to First
con convince the world that these people
their culture is barbaric it's primitive
it's backward it is everything bad that
you could imagine so that's where the
atrocity narrative against India begins
and that's all taught as standard
history in in today's Indian textbooks
okay that's why Indians are all Indians
most Indians have this tremendous
inferiority complex so you are right the
uh gami you're right that the game was
prepared before M arrived in India so M
came to India as as their best player
and then he played his Innings you're
right now about this downward filtration
Theory uh let's let's Google this guy
Duff this guy was a Scottish missionary
let's go to our friend Google once again
what does Google have to say about this
gentleman this individual huh Alexander
Duff Alexander Duff he was Scottish if I
am not mistaken let's go to Wikipedia
because they will say good things about
him obviously was the Scottish Church of
Scotland yes I think he was Scottish he
was born in Perth Scotland so a
scientific liberal reformer of
anglicized evangelism across the Empire
he founded the Scottish Church College
he established he played a role in
establishing the University of Kolkata K
Kolkata and so on so forth
and so one second where is the downward
filtration Theory
um where is it okay downward filter
Theory so this guy I think in the
1930s proposed what he called the
downward filter theory in which he
believed that by catering to the upper
the middle and upper social classes the
knowledge of Christianity would
eventually filter down the social
ladder he he promoted the teaching of
English and schools but he still viewed
the vernacular as an important language
for spreading Christianity his objective
was to spread Christianity not not
knowledge the same goes for this guy
mcau so M was not a missionary was not
an evangelist he was an
imperialist he wanted India to be fully
subjugated by the British and to do that
he wanted to he said that we have to
destroy the Indian education
system uh prevent these individuals from
studying in their own civilizational and
languages and mother tongu so Sanskrit
and whatever other tongues they have and
English should be the med medium of
education and the objective of the
education system to should be to create
a class of collaborators who may be
Brown by in skin but they are white
inside who idolize and worship the white
man and the British and who serve the
interest of the British Empire but they
don't have any leadership qualities and
they can be clerks and peons at best and
that's the education system you have in
India
today okay so that's what frustrates me
so much about today's education system
and that's why I go on these
uh yeah you know that's why I speak
about it so much so um the downward
filtration Theory or down to filter
Theory it's the same thing Maka said
that we have to uh give social give
upward Mobility to Indians only if they
are educated in the English language and
they are collaborators of the for the
British uh and and he he ensured that
there there in in British there could be
no progress or advancement in life
without English language education and
that still exists in India today and his
his uh theory was that or his objective
was that the collaborators who would
eventually be the cream of Indian
Society the elite of Indian Society
everybody would try and aspire to be
like them and those British ideals and
British you know
uh all of that would would would then
filter downwards and eventually after
decades and centuries all Indians would
become anglicized isn't that what's
happened today it's been super
successful so U I think mcau spoke about
the downward filtration filter Theory
whatever it was in in
1935 and it looks like this guy
Alexander Duff proposed that also
sometime in the 1930s maybe it is
Alexander Duff who said said this before
M maybe it's all right it's it's
possible
yeah okay next question
okay we're going to have to fight this
battle
again the next question if it appears
okay s borya says the brahui language a
dravidian tribal
language uh comes in Northern India and
did not contain the lawn words from old
Iranian aest and PTO but contains words
from the Balo language doesn't this
debunk the claim that har with Davidian
I'm not sure if the brahui language has
any connection with the harappans or
with the people of the Saras Sindu
region even though the brahi language
exists where you had Hara so once again
let's go to Google and and look for
brahui shall
we so that we can see the geographical
distribution of the brahui language
people whatever
so this is where you have it as you can
see it's in
baluchistan okay and this is apparently
a map of the so-called dravidian
language
so the so there is a this this spot in
in Pakistan pres of Pakistan in bistan
which is the region where people speak
the brahui language now let's see what
Wikipedia once again has to say once
again Wikipedia is not reliable but
let's just take a look at what this
article looks like so the bra not the
brahi people uh the brahi language brahi
language okay so it says it's it's a
davidan language are we sure about that
history Etc dialects phology blah blah
blah blah blah blah ET pers it has the
perso Arabic script all right uh okay
let's take a look at this the brahui
Lexicon is believed to be about 35%
perso Arabic origin okay 35% of the
vocabulary is Persian and Arabic 20% is
baloi origin baloi is is an Indo Arian
language or Indo Iranian language
classifi that's how it's classified
linguistically so 35 % Persian Arabic
20% beloi 20% Indo Arian and 15%
dravidian 10%
unknown so according to this research
which is from these books that are cited
over here which I can't open the
citations are of a couple of books here
so according to this research it's only
it only has about 15% dravidian words
now the same researchers will also say
that that Ric Sanskrit also had raan
loan
words so then isn't Ric s also a
dravidian language from that perspective
I mean your logic has to be consistent
doesn't it so according to Wikipedia
itself brahui has about 15% dravidian
words now I haven't gone into detail and
tried to see what words are of dravidian
origin but it looks like it's mostly 30%
person Arabic 20% baloi 20% Indo Arian
15%
dravidian so if the smallest
contribution is dravidian how can you
claim it's a dravidian language I'm not
sure how it works but U there seems to
be something fishy going on here okay
I'm not sure how Davidian this language
is I mean what can Tamil people or or or
Canada speaking people or Telugu
speaking people understand brahi I doubt
it very
much uh so that's what I would say I
find this not very
convincing and I am not sure if it has
any relationship with the ancient uh
people who once lived in this region and
the language they spoke which is the the
people of the Saras Hindu era of of our
our our history and I'm not sure when
the brahui speaking people arrived in
this region did they migrate from
somewhere else or is this a language
that has existed here for centuries
thousands of years we don't know that
okay so I would
I would raise a tremendous great amount
of skepticism when it comes to brahi
whether it is a dravidian language at
all if it only has according to
Wikipedia itself just
15% you know dravidian vocabulary there
are Scholars of Sanskrit who claim that
even the rigveda has so-called dravidian
loan words so by that same logic would
that not make the Ric Sanskrit also a
dravidian language
right
anyhow next question okay I'm going to
again have to fight this
battle uh come on here we are Sangita
says how did Rosevelt become the US
president three times Well actually
Theodore roselt was US president four
times was it Franklin
roselt uh one second
ruselt four times president
which okay it was Franklin D ruselt not
Theodore not Teddy it was Franklin
roselt who was president of the US four
times not three times so how did that
happen because in the US you have a
two-term limit right I mean Obama wanted
to still be in power but he had to demit
office after two
terms the same happened with Clinton and
so on so forth right so what happened
how did this guy roselt become president
four times 1932 he won 1936 he won 1940
he won he he won in 1944 again and he
became the president for the fourth time
and died early into his tenure as the
fourth during his fourth term as
president how did this happen first of
all he was clearly popular and secondly
there was no term limits in those days
but after he was elected four times the
the US Constitution was amended there
some amendment in the Constitution and a
two-term limit was was then encoded in
the US constit tion I think in the 1950s
early
1950s because of this four-time
presidency of of roselt so he became
president four times because there was
no term limit at that time
okay okay Annabeth Jackson says how to
increase confidence and train yourself
to not be too soft-hearted sorry not a
history geopolitics question I think
confidence comes from competence
whatever you do if you're really comp
competent super competent with that that
makes you confident so if you are let's
say an athlete and you're not good
enough then obviously you won't be
competent uh confident but if you're
super competent you do everything better
than everybody else confidence will be
naturally there and whatever else you do
whether you are in whatever occupation
profession whether you're a student if
you are super competent you're going to
be super confident so confidence if you
want to increase it you have to become
competent really competent better than
the vast majority of your peers in
whatever activity whatever field
whatever domain whatever industry
whatever thing it is you are in that's
the
simple answer even though it's it's
really hard to do that but that's how
you increase confidence
soft-hearted I don't know being
soft-hearted is it is it bad to be
soft-hearted what does it mean to be
soft-hearted I'm not sure but uh be be
com competent that's what I would say
not sure about what to say about being
soft-hearted should you be hard-hearted
I think that's not good uh you should be
fair I would say you should be fair
Don't Be Cruel don't be hard-hearted
don't be soft-hearted just be fair
that's it that that's that's enough be
competent be
fair next question is by lero online a
question related to music a German
origin musical artist group called
craftwork launched the musical album man
machine in the middle of 1978 but their
music sounded quite insane different
from the contemporary music genres the
Beats sound similar to today's popular
electronic dance music really I don't
think so I think it sounds very
different very
unique even today if you listen to
craftwork and man machine the album it
sounds at the same time retro as well as
40 years in the
future it doesn't sound like today's
electronic dance music from from my
perspective okay even today it sounds
futuristic but retro it's weird and that
music is so addtive that one cannot stop
it without finishing the track how did
they produce uh how did they produce
such Music 50 years in the past well
you've always had some people who could
produce tremendous
uh who there's always been people who
think different who are creative and who
are unlike everybody else so let me give
so craftwork is a great example let me
give you another example uh let us go to
Google and there is an there is a genre
of music called acid house so let's
let's uh
acid
tracks by pure yeah so this comes out
when in 1987 or 88 and uh I will not
play the music obviously over here
because it would give me a copyright
strike but it is very much available on
YouTube I think it's from 1988 and this
is the music track which is insane
actually if you listen to it it's got
that uh what what I forget the the the
instrument that's used the 303
right no no no not this okay it's it's
got It's got a very unique sound the
kind of sound that was never heard
before and it is considered to be this
track was was considered to be the
originator of the acid house genre and
it it it came out in 1987 or 88 but then
they discovered an album from 1980 10
ragas to a disco beat by charanjit sing
from 1980 a Bollywood
musician okay and if you listen to it
that is actually the first acid
house album so there have been musicians
like these who are completely obscure
whose music never took off at the time
but today if you listen to it you'll be
blown away and it's clearly something
that is far ahead of its time so
there've always been people like these
but that music is not for most people
most people don't want get it even today
so you got to be a real music conosur to
to be able to get such music and to
enjoy such music so I'm sure craft work
did were not a huge
success it's it's kind of an obscure
band today I'm sure future and acid
cracks most people want to know about it
I'm sure most people don't know about
the late charanjit Singh who who passed
away a few years ago but these people
have been the Pioneers who remembers
Nick
Drake almost no one does he was the van
go of Music he died at the age of 26
there so many so many such great
musicians who came and did something
completely unique and then disappeared
and you you discover their
music uh decades later decades later
uh yeah I can give you more examples but
I I won't go and do that because I could
spend two hours doing that I could I
could spend two hours digging out
unknown gems that I am aware of but I
won't be able to play play the music
first of all because you can't do that
it's again against YouTube uh you know
rules
so okay I have I'm at the end of the
questions I have selected let's take
some questions from the live
chat okay let's take some questions from
the live chat uh D kth is giving another
suggestion Minute Man by Beck is it Beck
or is it Jeff Beck Jeff Beck was a
guitar player I think he passed away a
few years ago recently he was part of
the Yard Birds and then he and one of
the members of The Yard Birds was Jimmy
Page and then the Yard Birds broke up
and Jimmy Pig created a new band called
the new Yard Birds which eventually
became lead Zeppelin so I'm not sure if
minute minute math is by Jeff back Beck
or some other Beck but I will certainly
check this out thank you for the
recommendation I really appreciate that
um okay Aram asks a question that I kind
of took up it's the first question of
this this live stream what's my view on
Rishi shuk's defeat in the UK and how
much it will affect India I am not
surprised that he's been defeated
um he did not achieve anything
significant anything stupendous he was
just another guy and the new guy who's
come to power is again going to be just
another guy who will do nothing special
significant or memorable so it makes no
difference to the rest of the world it
makes no difference to India it doesn't
make any difference to the UK much and
for the US it's business as as usual so
nothing it doesn't surprise me I kind of
expected this it's it's a landslide
victory for the other guy starmer and it
doesn't really affect the rest of the
world it's not going to affect the India
UK relationship at all in my
opinion Phoenix op says when can India
build its own Flagship jet like the
American B2 stealth bomber well I would
like a B1 first the Boone we don't have
any strategic bombers the way
we don't have any we've never bothered
to to develop any the Chinese have have
knockoffs of Russ of Russian bombers so
the B2 Ste bomber is that flying wing
shaped thing do you want to take a look
at what it looks like we could do that
let's go to
Google B2
bomber what's it look like this is what
it looks like all right the Flying
Wing uh and this is the kind of stuff
goodies that it didn't carry
um and this is obviously a knockoff of a
Nazi era Nazi
plane so that thing was called the hon
ho229 from the Second World War era can
you imagine how far ahead of the times
the the German Engineers were they
developed this
thing decades before anyone even
imagined the B2 stealth bomber so okay
that's the div verion digression from
from the question which I am kind of I
kind of do often but the point is when
can India do this so I think we have
something that we are developing right
now called the aura or the gatak which
is a flying wing prototype and it's
going to be an unmanned vehicle
aircraft and once it and I I I'm sure we
have done a few tests of that you know a
few demonstrations tests of the of the
concept A small scale down version and
eventually we have a full scale version
of that hopefully soon and if that goes
fine we could even put a couple of
people in there and make it even larger
so I think we are on the way to doing
that but I'm not sure if it's going to
be a strategic bomber maybe it's going
to be an unmanned vehicle an unmanned
stealth stealth uh aircraft but once you
have the flying design which actually
works you can scale it up and you know
convert that if if you can into a
stealth uh strategic bomber if you can
so I'm sure we can do it but you need a
government green light for that and you
you need funding for that and will the
Indian government fund that thing I'm
not sure but it can can be
done all
right so this is a hypothetical question
by
Shri ratsa what could have happened if
the Mongols with the leadership of
chingis Khan had decided on a fullscale
invasion of India what were the major
things that might have changed
throughout our history well they would
have taken out the turn
because who was leading who who was
ruling India at the time it was the
Turks who were ruling India so uh they
would have taken out the Turks and they
would have imposed Mongol rule in India
and then maybe India Destiny would have
been entirely different you cannot even
begin to speculate what what would have
happened there would have been no turkey
rule in India there would have been
Mongolian rule in India and the Mongols
were overall not as
horrific when it comes to compared to
the Turks I me obviously they are they
have very bad reputation because they
took out entire empires in very short
amount of time amounts of time the
Chinese they take they took they
defeated the whole of China they
defeated the whole the entire kism
Empire which obviously is going to cause
casualties when you when you conquer
that enormous amount of territory it
will cause casualties that's why the
Mongols have a very very bad name and
reputation but if they had uh launched
an invasion of India they would not I
imagine
have well you know uh targeted the
civilians they would have targeted the
the rulers who are the Turks so I'm just
speculating this is actually an exercise
in speculation what could have happened
well here we are today we don't know all
right
uh okay man says what's going on in the
SE meeting I believe uh well I've not
really kept
much kept too much of of track of what's
happening there I think shabas Sharif
Sharif the Pakistan guy has gone there
and uh I'm sure he met Mr Putin he would
have met Mr shei as well Putin and she
would have met and
U uh they would have met Central Asian
leaders and so on and and Dr joser is
there and he has made certain St he has
put forth India's perspective on this uh
you know uh respecting sovereignty uh
cracking down on terrorism and so on so
forth so that's the kind of stuff that's
going on there we have chosen to to not
give too much importance to the SEO this
time and I think it's the right choice
that we have made the Prime Minister has
made
okay alone traveler says questions about
food music Etc really interesting I
think it's very interesting I think I'm
I find these topics very interesting
culture music food Cuisine traveling I
enjoy that I
agree
uh red says why are the pashun and
bachis classified as Iranians or iranic
it's because the Western historians have
decided that the baches and the and the
pashun are Iranian
iranic and that's why everybody believes
that including the balois and the bhun I
mean if you say to a pashon that you
people are actually subcontinental
people who are much closer to to India
than Iran then they get offended they
say no no no how dare you say that we
know who we are we have always been
different we have been different for
2,000 years we are the graveyard of
Empires we are different from India we
are more Iranian than Indian and we are
actually descendants of Jews that's what
they will claim because that's what
they've been brainwashed into
believing and obviously if you go to
gandha Afghanistan today there's a lot
of foreign DNA there which is non pushu
nonlocal there's a lot of turkic DNA in
the population now hazaras pans KES Etc
the tajiks are still Indo Iranian but
but there's a lot of foreign non Afghan
DNA in Afghanistan today and that's a
consequence of the foreign occupation
tkic occupation of Afghanistan which has
been going on for the past thousand
years so obviously foreign attitudes
foreign DNA Etc has prated into the into
the
Consciousness so the pashun now believe
that they have nothing to do with India
the language they believe it's it's an
iranic
language listen to bash does it sound
Iranian or does it sound Indian it kind
of sounds somewhere in between but there
is a
clear Indian accent in there okay in the
PTO language when it comes to the baloi
language oh man come on they are so much
closer to the people of Cinda and
sashtra than to the people of Persia the
balois they don't even look Persian by
the way the buoi people what are you
talking about but they believe the so
it's because of the western historians
and their influence that everyone
believes
this endan says some universities in
India like so and so University are
openly breeding valkism in India and
students are being brainwashed to become
anti-hindu and anti- Indian why is the
government being so soft on these issues
well you will have to ask the government
of
India we we need to have very clear
policies about these
matters the education system the purpose
of the education system is to
create confident
young citizens and Future Leaders who
will take the nation forward not hate
the nation so if the education system is
not serving the purpose then you need
there's a major problem in the education
system and in case certain universities
whether it's X or Y University or Z
University that's doing this more than
other universities then there's a
problem there so I don't know why this
is allowed to go on and on and on but
there's a problem you I've been saying
this for forever essentially the
government needs to take education
seriously and we need to have reforms
it's not happening and it is extremely
disappointing missed
opportunity um okay
Arian Knight says why can India not use
Afghanistan as a proxy against Pakistan
listen you have to be really powerful to
be able to use a nation as a proxy
against there especially when that
nation is already being used as a proxy
by the
US okay geopolitics is in is extremely
complicated Afghanistan is already a US
proxy the Taliban did not defeat the us
and take Afghanistan the Americans
handed Afghanistan to the Taliban on a
platter they Left Behind hundred billion
dollar worth of arms and ammunition for
the Taliban and they are allegedly
giving the Taliban a stipend of 50 or80
million in cash every week so that is
clearly a US proxy us wasal you think
you can take the American proxy and make
it Indian proxy you think Americans will
allow that you think that's how the
world Works doesn't work like that so
from the US perspective Pakistan is a
counterbalance to India no
in an Ideal World for the Americans
India is a counterbalance to China but
India also should not become too strong
so Pakistan is a counterbalance to India
but Pakistan also should behave so
Afghanistan is a counterbalance to
Pakistan that is the game The Americans
are playing all right that's what's
happening and there's nothing you can do
about it unless you are powerful enough
and India is not powerful enough right
now is India in a position to give more
to the thir to the Taliban and to keep
the Americans away India is
not Lucario says did Rak lose because of
racism no no nothing to do with racism
it was just time for him to for his
party to lose
and what did he achieve in in his one
year 300 days or 200 days in power
nothing nothing much so it was just
going to happen everybody expected this
everybody who understands anything about
the UK's politics expected this to
happen I don't think there's anything to
do with uh anything about racism in
this uh
okay lots of questions being repeated
for some reason but okay let's see some
other questions
um
uh Tipo Master says it looks like do the
French company that makes theal fight a
plane is bulking at the de transfer
Clause of the new Union government
should India reconsider the F-15 EX4 MC
mrca should India should Russia apply
its Su 57 to8 listen that these are all
complicated matters nobody will be
willing to give up
extremely extremely sensitive technology
without extracting a tremendous amount
of value in return for it so this they
know that India desperately needs jet
engine technology techology world class
jet engine
technology so they will obviously
negotiate as hard as
possible that's to be understood it's
not like the French are our enemies they
if we G give enough in in exchange they
may be willing to transfer the
technology but it will come at a huge
price for sure now is that price
something we are willing to pay that's
for the government to decide I
think we need the technology somehow
anyway one way or the other we need that
whether from the French from the
Americans from the Russians whoever but
nobody will give that up just that
easily so I think India needs to find a
way to get it okay uh F-15 I don't think
India should get any American fighter
planes I don't think India should even
get Russian fighter planes we need to
build our own fighter plane
families we need to build better and
better iterative versions of the Tes f a
plane we need to build the advanced
medium combat aircraft we need to build
whatever other comes in thing comes in
the
future uh we need to have spin-offs of
these fighter jet families and we need
to anyhow have our own jet engine once
we have a jet engine even if it is not
superpowered even if it is what 80 kons
or whatever build a fighter plane with
two jet engines and we fine so we need
to find our own way of doing this and
and if possible just buy the technology
at whatever price it comes that's that's
how I see it but I don't want India to
buy any new fighter planes any new
fighter plane variants from other
countries if you already have the the
Rafal then you can buy more because you
know how to deal with that but no new F
F15 or whatever
else unless you have a production line
in your country which you control so
that's how I see it
gorov says both how are both Voyager
spacecrafts still operational and able
to send back valuable scientific data
despite being more than 20 billion
kilometers away from the earth alert
Space Rock incoming look it takes about
it takes more than 20 hours from for the
light signal for the radio signal to
from Earth to reach the spacecraft and
the same amount of time for their the
spacecraft signals to reach Earth
because they're so far away the speed of
light is a limit right you cannot go
beyond faster than that but they are
still
operational with 1970s technology and uh
today in NASA there are a bunch of
scientists A bunch of Engineers who
specialize in the technology just
because these spacecraft are still
operational so they have been well
designed well built well there were some
glitches now because of the advanced age
of the spacecraft but they are still
somehow communicating and hopefully
they'll continue continue to communicate
for a few more few more
years okay
now
uh any other questions that I could take
up we have crossed the two hour mark so
I should end this
soon um Summit statement said we says we
had peace when power was in
patliputra how can we achieve the unity
again and ensure that no one feels
subjugated but rather United for power
peace and prosperity from Nepal
look it's
impossible for no one to feel subjugated
there will always be people who have
grievances no matter how big your Empire
is no matter how small your kingdom is
even if you have a city state with a
population of just a
100,000 even then you will have people
who feel subjugated and
unhappy so it is impossible for everyone
to feel that we are all United and blah
blah blah there will always be Mal
content
and people with with grievances Etc
there's nothing we can do about it the
question is how do we achieve the unity
again all of us right that can only
happen when the right come kind of
leader comes comes
about is there any leader of the caliber
of Chandra Gupta MAA today or Ashok
morya or
keska or or or Kumar Gupta or
skandagupta or samudra Gupta or l v or M
or chhatrapati shagi Maharaj do we have
or or or or Raj rajendra cha do we have
any leaders of the caliber today we have
no such leaders
today that sort of unity can only happen
when we have a leader of that caliber
and we have no such leaders today
compared to the great today's leaders
are
mediocre it's only a leader with
tremendous abilities and tremendous
willpower who can
unite a nation that is the the that is
the size of a
subcontinent so hopefully some such
leader has emerged has been born by now
and uh that's what we can say so it's
because leadership is more important
than whatever else you can never ensure
that everybody feels happy they will
always be Mal contents no matter how
well you
rule an Empire a country or whatever so
but yes it would be great to see all of
us United again
and India the
subcontinent becoming great again as it
has always
been okay let's take one more question
uh let's take something that hopefully
have not taken
before uh no I only know of one book so
any other suggestions about a book to
learn Sanskrit from except from Sanskrit
shika shik Shak I can only offer that
one suggestion Sanskrit swam shik Shak
you study that that if you study that
properly over a period of 3 to six
months properly like really rigorously
then you will be able to have a
conversational hold on Sanskrit and then
you can do Advanced study of your own
just by purchasing the original srit
version of the ramayan Mahabharat R
whatever and taking it forward that's
what I would suggest you do and Arian
Knight is resending to Future acid
tracks along with my video awesome you
discover it awesome love
it
uh Phoenix says do you think the
Japanese people think of Japan as a US
wasal state or a Sovereign Nation Most
Japanese people think of Japan as a
Sovereign Nation if you are a wasal and
if if if I am a hegemonic power who is
ruling over a wasal I will ensure that
that wasal states education system
teaches the people that they are
free that's how you can perpetuate your
hold over a nation so so I think most
Japanese people are not aware of the
fact that they are not a Sovereign
Nation that they are under permanent US
military
occupation
uh uh what else what else what
else rajat says how can you how to
minimize Stress For Life well everybody
has their own path own way of doing it
you have to take good care of yourself
you have to eat good food have a good
lifestyle healthy lifestyle uh be
physically active lift weights sleep
eight hours a day or whatever works for
you and uh be competent in whatever
you're doing and then to hell with
everybody else and what they think if
you place a lot of importance on what
other people's people their opinions are
then you will always have stress so
that's what I would
say and we shall
now um
okay Karan says in spite of having so
much solar energy why are we dependent
on coal is it practically possible to
achieve kardashev level one following
you from first episode thank you so much
that's amazing thank you so much okay I
I really appreciate that I really
appreciate all of you who have been
following me who have been participating
really appreciate that uh we are still
dependent on coal because we are
technologically not that great right our
governments they they
what can I say the emphasis has never
been on on on technological
Excellence hopefully now it is going to
be more like that I I'm not saying the
present government is like that but
historically our governments have cared
nothing about the country and its people
that's why we have been so mediocre so
yeah I think we should certainly have a
significant emphasis on solar energy and
India is now the founder the the
founding member of the international
solar Alliance an initiative by Prime
Minister Modi which one has to really
appreciate and we are now making good
strides in in that direction but we are
still dependent on the Legacy technology
which is heavily cold dependent so it'll
take time for this to change but we are
hopefully moving in the right direction
second question is it practically
possible to achieve kardashev level one
it is possible for sure but it may take
a lot of time but it's certainly
possible to control the entire energy
that's available on one planet it is
certainly possible theoretically will
humans achieve that I am not sure but if
we do it'll be great I'll be happy
and
uh om B says willm replace x86 in the
future I am not
sure not
sure maybe maybe not I'm not really
sure
uh steps for raising standards knowledge
Seeker I think I'll make a video about
that because you can't just give steps
in a couple of minutes I think there has
to be a separate video recorded video
about that but I will do
that and with that I think I'm going
[Music]
to geopolitical Du says political
turmoil in Nepal again this time o plus
plus Sher bahad deba that goes on that
goes on that goes on there's always be
always going to be the sort of
thing pret Agarwal says 1 million party
okay let's reach 1 million then we'll do
something uh okay okay let's end this
session today the two 100th episode of
ask abijit so I'm going to end it over
here thank you so much to all of you
once again I really appreciate
everybody's support I would not be here
doing this without your participation
without your support so thank you so
much I really appreciate that and we
will continue this going forward and we
may
reach uh episode numbers that we may not
have imagined today so thank you so much
once again thank you once again to ramal
lakmi and everybody else who has been
contributing so much to to this
community I really really appreciate all
of you thank you so much and I'll see
you in the next live stream keep raising
his standards bye